Guide to the Theodore E. Steinway Collection of Steinway & Sons Ephemera circa 1860-1986 MS 3181
New-York Historical Society
Theodore E. Steinway collection of Steinway & Sons ephemera
circa 1860-1986
New-York Historical Society
Steinway, Theodore E., 1883-1957.
MS 3181
8 Linear feet in 11 boxes.
Material on the history of renowned piano makers Steinway & Sons, and other manufacturers, largely assembled by company president Theodore E. Steinway (1883–1957), author of People and Pianos: A Century of Service to Music: Steinway & Sons, New York, 1853–1953. The collection includes some photographs, a few financial reports, and a wealth of ephemera, including advertisements, brochures, trade catalogs, newspaper clippings, sheet music, a run of concert programs from Steinway Hall (1876–1890), and transcripts of Theodore Steinway's commentary for WQXR Radio's Tuesday evening broadcasts of recorded piano music from Symphony Hall (1941–1942).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry Z. and John H. Steinway, 1987.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in five series:
Series I.
Programs, 1866–1979
Series II.
Advertising, 1860–1986
Series III.
Piano catalogs, circa 1870–1950
Series IV.
Sheet music, 1870s–1898, undated
Series V.
Miscellaneous, 1865–1974, undated
Biographical / Historical
Theodore Edwin Steinway (1883–1957) was a grandson of Henry E. Steinway (1797–1871), who founded the famed piano manufacturing firm of Steinway & Sons in Manhattan in 1853. In 1864 Theodore's father, William Steinway (1835–1896), opened Steinway Hall, a lavish performance venue to showcase the company's instruments, at 109 East 14th Street (it housed the New York Philharmonic until Carnegie Hall opened in 1891; a later Steinway Hall opened at 111 West 57th Street in 1925). Beginning in the 1870s, William moved operations to Queens, establishing around the piano factory a company town called Steinway Village to house his craftsmen and their families (it is now part of the neighborhood of Astoria). Theodore Steinway served as president of the firm from 1927 to 1955, and then as chairman of the board from 1955 until his death just two years later. Theodore's son, Henry Ziegler Steinway (1915–2008), was the last member of the family to head Steinway & Sons before its sale in 1972.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society also holds:
• Steinway & Sons Photograph and Print Collection, 1858–1949 (PR 166).
• Papers of Ralph Tapp, 1936–1946 (BV Tapp), a Steinway & Sons salesman.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains material largely assembled by Steinway & Sons president Theodore Edwin Steinway (1883–1957), author of the 1953 company history People and Pianos: A Century of Service to Music: Steinway & Sons, New York, 1853–1953. It includes a wealth of ephemera—advertisements, brochures, manufacturers' catalogs, newspaper clippings, sheet music—some photographs, and (minimal) financial reports, as well as a substantial run of programs for concerts held at Steinway Hall (1876–1890), the firm's self-built performance venue and showroom at 109 East 14th Street, Manhattan (in use 1864–1925). Also present are transcripts of Theodore Steinway's commentary for WQXR Radio's Tuesday evening broadcasts of recorded piano music from Symphony Hall (1941–1942).
Separated Materials
The gift of this collection included a photocopied set of the ten-volume diary of William E. Steinway, covering 1861–1896. It has been cataloged separately (click here for the record). Rather than request it, researchers should consult the digitized originals via the Smithsonian Institution: americanhistory.si.edu/steinwaydiary/.
A description of the collection when it came to the New-York Historical Society in 1987 mentions that it also included a "rolled map of NYC with notes about Revolutionary War" and seven scrapbooks of concert and theatre programs (1908–1917) assembled by Frederick T. Steinway (1860–1927). These items were not found when the collection was examined in January 2022.
Advertisements.; Brochures.; Concert programs.; Ephemera.; Financial records.; Manufacturers' catalogs.; Newspaper clippings.; Photographs.; Sheet music.; Transcripts.; Concerts.; Music.; Piano.; Piano makers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Steinway piano.; Steinway & Sons; Steinway Hall (New York, N.Y.); Steinway (Family); WQXR (Radio station: New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. Programs, 1866–1979
  - Steinway Hall programs [3 folders], 1866–1876 (Offsite-box 2)
    Related Materials
    Includes Theodore E. Steinway's handwritten list of what he could find. Possibly Steinway & Sons was the first to print up a program and furnish it to the user with the hire of the Hall, and then sell ads in the program to make it self sustaining.
    See also the 14 volumes of the "Steinway Hall Programme," 1876–1890, in boxes 9 and 10.
  - Programs at other halls [2 folders], circa 1874–1965 (Offsite-box 2)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. I, 1876 (Sep.)–1877 (May) (Offsite-box 9)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. II, 1877 (Oct.)–1878 (May) (Offsite-box 9)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. III, 1878 (Sep.)–1879 (May) (Offsite-box 9)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. IV, 1879 (Oct.)–1880 (May) (Offsite-box 9)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. V, 1880 (Oct.)–1881 (May) (Offsite-box 9)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. VI, 1881 (Oct.)–1882 (May) (Offsite-box 9)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. VII, 1882 (Nov.)–1883 (May) (Offsite-box 9)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. VIII, 1883 (Oct.)–1884 (May) (Offsite-box 10)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. IX, 1884 (Oct.)–1885 (May) (Offsite-box 10)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. X, 1885 (Oct.)–1886 (May) (Offsite-box 10)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. XI, 1886 (Oct.)–1887 (May) (Offsite-box 10)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. XII, 1887 (Nov.)–1888 (Apr.) (Offsite-box 10)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. XIII, 1888 (Nov.)–1889 (Apr.) (Offsite-box 10)
  - Steinway Hall Programme, Vol. XIV, 1889 (Nov.)–1890 (May) (Offsite-box 10)
  - Volume of "Intimate Recitals, Steinway Hall, 14th Street & 57th Street", 1921–1923 (Offsite-box 10)
    Scope and Contents
    Despite this volume's cover inscription, it contains no programs from the 57th Street location of Steinway Hall.
  - Programs of various events, anniversaries, etc. [2 folders], 1894–1960 (Offsite-box 4-A)
  - Programs of various events, anniversaries, etc. [3 folders], 1962–1979 (Offsite-box 4-B)
- Series II. Advertising, 1860–1986
  - Old piano ads and ephemera (non-Steinway) [5 folders], 1860–1900 (Offsite-box 1)
    These envelopes contain Theodore E. Steinway's collection of all kinds of ads and tear sheets of non-Steinway material.
  - Info collected on Daniel F. Beatty [1 folder], 1870s–1880s (Offsite-box 1)
    Material on Beatty of Washington, N.J., who sold pianos and organs entirely by direct mail. (Beatty, who also collected stamps, was of particular interest to Theodore E. Steinway, who, in addition to heading Steinway & Sons, was a noted philatelist.)
  - Steinway advertising brochures, circa 1934–1986 (Offsite-box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings of Steinway ads, circa 1860–1940s (Offsite-box 7)
    Theodore E. Steinway attempted to get as many early Steinway ads as he could from the company's early address in Walker Street, from 14th Street before the number change, etc.
- Series III. Piano catalogs, circa 1870–1950
  - Piano and organ catalogs, and some Victor Talking Machine pamphlets [2 folders], 1870–1900 (Offsite-box 2)
  - Manufacturers' catalogs (non-Steinway) [4 folders], circa 1900–1950 (Offsite-box 5)
- Series IV. Sheet music, 1870s–1898, undated
  - Johann Strauss Waltzes, undated (Offsite-box 8)
  - Photostat of Richard Wagner's Festmarsch composed for the Philadelphia Centennial Exhibition, 1876 (Offsite-box 8)
  - Compositions by Nahum Stetson, 1870s–1880s (Offsite-box 8)
    Nahum Stetson (1856–1933) was sales manager of Steinway, 1876–1930.
  - "Steinway-Valse pour Piano" by E. Moullé, 1898 (Offsite-box 8)
    Dedicated in memoriam to William Steinway (1835–1896) by E. Moullé, Paris. Moulle were Steinway agents for France.
- Series V. Miscellaneous, 1865–1974, undated
  - Photos and written material of keyboard instruments [2 folders], undated (Offsite-box 2)
  - Booklet on opera in German, circa 1900 (Offsite-box 2)
    "New Yorker Revue Opern-Textbuch" (condensed opera plots).
  - Map of Paris (1867 Exposition Universelle) (Offsite-box 2)
  - Obituary of Henry Steinway Jr. and 3 letters to the company, 1865–1974 (Offsite-box 3)
    The obituary of Henry Steinway Jr. (1831–1865) appears on p. 53 of Western Musical World, vol. 2, no. 4 (April 1865). The three letters are dated 1964, 1968, and 1974.
  - Financial reports, 1939–1969 (Offsite-box 3)
    • Reports on Examination, 1941–1948 [1 folder]
    • Annual Reports, 1939–1969 (scattered issues; some include President's Report) [2 folders]
    • Accountants' certificates, 1942–1947 [1 folder]
    • President's reports, 1940–1947 [1 folder]
  - Theodore E. Steinway's WQXR radio transcripts [1 folder], 1941–1942 (Offsite-box 3)
    As reported by the Brooklyn Daily Eagle, Thursday 4 September 1941, p. 20, col. 1: "WQXR announces a new series of Tuesday 'Symphony Hall' programs featuring recorded piano music by famous artists, starting next Tuesday [9 September 1941] at 8 p.m. Theodore E. Steinway will serve as commentator."